<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Michele Ferretti</title>
    <description>Society, Technology and Cities.</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>ACHILLES</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;ACHILLES:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Demo awarded 2nd Place at the DataSpark Mobility Challenge organized by
the International Conference on Information and Knowledge Management
(CIKM) - Singapore, Nov. 2017&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Background: The availability of massive datasets describing human
mobility offer the possibility to monitor and improve the resilience of
transportation systems to traumatic events such as disasters of natural
or anthropocentric origin. In this perspective, we propose a visual,
data-driven and network-based simulation tool based on a multiplex
network representation of mobility data, where every layer describes
movement of people’s with a given trans- portation mode. We then develop
a visual analytics tool which provides an easy-to-use interface to
explore the mobility uxes and the connectivity of every urban zone in a
city. Our visual analytics tool allows the user to visualize changes in
the transportation system resulting from the addition or removal of
transportation modes, urban zones and single stops. We show how our
visual system can be used to explore mobility in Singapore, by using
data provided by the CIKM challenge 2017 and Singapore mobility data
obtained from external sources. e system allows to simulate the reaction
to changes in the Singapore’s public trans- portation system, such as
closing/adding transportation modes or subway/bus stops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;year-2017&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Year&lt;/strong&gt;: 2017&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;client-uncommissioned&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Client&lt;/strong&gt;: uncommissioned&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;team-michele-ferretti-gianni-barlacchi-luca-pappalardo&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Team&lt;/strong&gt;: “Michele Ferretti, Gianni Barlacchi, Luca Pappalardo”&lt;/h4&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/achille/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/achille/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Telecom Big Data Challenge</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In the spring of 2013 I had the opportunity to attend a course on “Multivariate Statistics” at the Faculty of &lt;a href=&quot;https://mox.polimi.it/&quot;&gt;Mathematics Engineering&lt;/a&gt;, Politecnico di Milano. During the entire semester I worked on a project with a group of engineers, using the absolute volume of traffic (in Erlang) from mobile phone data, to model people’s presence and movement within Milan’s first urban belt, and derive a land-use classification based entirely on such data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;year-2013&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Year&lt;/strong&gt;: 2013&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;client-uncommissioned&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Client&lt;/strong&gt;: uncommissioned&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;team-michele-ferretti-roberto-pensa-paolo-terzi-luca-turconi&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Team&lt;/strong&gt;: Michele Ferretti, Roberto Pensa, Paolo Terzi, Luca Turconi&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/telecom/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/telecom/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Maptime Milano</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;“Maptime is an open learning environment for all levels and degrees of knowledge, offering intentional educational support for the beginner. Maptime is simultaneously flexible and structured, creating space for mapping tutorials, workshops, ongoing projects with a shared goal, and independent/collaborative work time.. (from :&lt;a href=&quot;http://maptime.io/about/&quot;&gt;maptime.io/about&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In December 2014 I started the &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MaptimeMI&quot;&gt;Milanese chapter&lt;/a&gt; in the amazing FabLab &lt;a href=&quot;opendotlab.it&quot;&gt;Opendot&lt;/a&gt;. Since then, we had the most fun and interesting nights, learning together web-mapping tools such as &lt;a href=&quot;leafletjs.com&quot;&gt;LeafletJS&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mapbox.com/mapbox-studio/#darwin&quot;&gt;Mapbox Studio&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this is just the beginning! In the next few months we’ll have various guest such as data journalist and designers, to teach us the best practices of storytelling and data visualization.
As always…&lt;em&gt;Beginners most welcome!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;year-ongoing-from-2014-monthly-basis&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Year&lt;/strong&gt;: ongoing from 2014 (monthly basis)&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;client-uncommissioned&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Client&lt;/strong&gt;: uncommissioned&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 04 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/maptime/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/maptime/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Death of Distance</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Despite a certain line of thought mainly developed across the end of the 90’s and the beginning of the 00’s, which claimed for a supposed “Death of Distance”, arguing for a “Flatter World” in respect to social and economic phenomena, hard evidence still seems to stand up for the contrary. The same spread of ICT and new communication technologies that supposedly would have put an “End to Geography”, has indeed provided plenty of data for successive studies that assessed the relevance of geographic dimension in shaping nowadays interactions between and within urban environments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thesis work aims to dwell further in the understanding of socio-economic processes mediated through space, and on their effects on the urban milieu, by exploiting, for its own analyses, data coming from the exact same technologies that the “World is Flat” hypothesis theorised as one of the pillars of the Globalization 3.0 homogeneous landscape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In doing so, it positions itself at the convergence of different research paths: Economics, Urban Studies, Social and Quantitative Research, Computational Informatics..hopefully providing an additional example of the usefulness and richness of applying Computer Science methodologies to innovative data sources harvested from the mobile phone sensors to the service of urban research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;year-2013&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Year&lt;/strong&gt;: 2013&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;client-uncommissioned&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Client&lt;/strong&gt;: uncommissioned&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/dod/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/dod/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Alpinescapes</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Following the agreement on the “European Landscape Convention” (European Commission, 2000) and the Joint Programme Initiative on “Cultural Heritage” (JPI Cultural Heritage, 2010) , a new operational definition of Landscape has been promoted in recent years by EU Institutions. In such definition, the Social Dimension of Landscape (which is henceforth viewed both as a social construct as well as social product (Castiglioni, 2009) ) has been posed at the heart of the matter (and consequently, at the core of any policy action involving such issue). The new Horizon 2020 programming directives will also push forward in the same  direction, by stressing the need to tackle Societal Challenges related to Cultural Heritage (European Commission, 2014) with new forms of innovation, enabled by a combination of modern ICT, such as social media and mobile technologies, combined with a shift towards more transparent and participative models of territorial governance for the public sector, such as the OpenGovernment and OpenData paradigms (European Commission, 2014).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building upon such premises, the Alpinescapes project poses itself as a novel tentative to link these multiple dimensions, by focusing on OpenData and Open licensing to collect, organise, provide access to and ultimately give back and contribute, to the existing open content on the alpine landscape (and its heritage, geography and anthropology…) of Valsassina valley in Northern Italy. Linking data from traditional Geographic Information Science repositories to Wikipedia and from local Public Institutions geo-databases to the crowdsourced planetary database of OpenStreetMap, the project aims at building an easy-to-use platform, not only for the promotion and exploration of the areas’ surroundings, but most crucially to enable the participative construction and representation of Valsassina’s landscape as perceived by its User/Citizens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;year-2014&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Year&lt;/strong&gt;: 2014&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;client--interreg-ita-ch-comunità-montana-della-valsassina-suspi-lugano-politecnico-di-milano&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Client&lt;/strong&gt;:  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.interreg-italiasvizzera.it/home-it&quot;&gt;INTERREG ITA-CH&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.valsassina.it/&quot;&gt;Comunità Montana della Valsassina&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.supsi.ch/home.html&quot;&gt;SUSPI-Lugano&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.polimi.it/&quot;&gt;Politecnico di Milano&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;team-daniele-villa-paolo-tagliolato-michele-ferretti&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Team&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/danielevilla&quot;&gt;Daniele Villa&lt;/a&gt;, Paolo Tagliolato, Michele Ferretti&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/alpinescapes/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/alpinescapes/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Nokia Data Challenge</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Research idea for the Nokia Mobile Data Challenge 2012 - Open Challenge Track&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Project Title: “Identification of significant places and life practices through mobile usage data: a urban analysis perspective”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Background: Urban analytics techniques appear to be increasingly inadequate in describing city dynamics such as urban spaces usages by temporary populations, which are inherently characterized by time-dependent intensity variations. A first consideration regards traditional sources for the analysis of daily mobility, an information through which it is possible to interpret daily urban practices. The main sources of data are surveys on commuters flows. They provide a very partial picture of daily practices in urban areas, because they collect only flows for job and study purposes. Therefore they are unable to describe the main components of urban mobility, that rapidly changes because of the occurrence of demographic, economic and social dynamics. Analyzing the spatial and temporal usage of cities in their contemporary daily-life practices requires an integration between traditional data (land cover, town plans, spatial distribution of activities, etc.) and new sources of information aimed at identifying the complexity and multiplicity of individual behaviors. Recognizing and mapping the flows and patterns of daily mobility, in their spatial and temporal dimensions, could be a major achievement in the understanding of contemporary city dynamics for Urban Studies and for Urban Planning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;year-2013&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Year&lt;/strong&gt;: 2013&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;client-uncommissioned&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Client&lt;/strong&gt;: uncommissioned&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;team-fabio-manfredini-paolo-tagliolato-michele-ferretti&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Team&lt;/strong&gt;: “Fabio Manfredini, Paolo Tagliolato, Michele Ferretti”&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/nokia/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/nokia/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Interactive Table</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;An interactive table commissioned by the milanese &lt;a href=&quot;www.ordinearchitetti.mi.it/&quot;&gt;Ordine degli Architetti di Milano&lt;/a&gt; -  Order of Architects PPC of the province of Milan to complement a photographic exhibition on the contemporary architectural landscape of Milan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;year-2015&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Year&lt;/strong&gt;: 2015&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;client-ordine-degli-architetti-di-milano-opendot&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Client&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;www.ordinearchitetti.mi.it/&quot;&gt;Ordine degli Architetti di Milano&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;www.opendotlab.it&quot;&gt;Opendot&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;team-alessandro-masserdotti-andreji-boleslavsky-ambhika-samsen-michele-ferretti&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Team&lt;/strong&gt;: Alessandro Masserdotti, Andreji Boleslavsky, Ambhika Samsen, Michele Ferretti&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jul 2012 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/interactive-table/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/interactive-table/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Tangible Map</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;An arduino-powered, 3d-printed map of Italy to physically represent statistical data (such as GDP, population density..).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each region is independently controlled by a stepper motor and moves along the z-axis due to an (also 3d-printed) rack mechanism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The complete documentation, along with the code and STL files will (hopefully) be online soon!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;year-2015&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Year&lt;/strong&gt;: 2015&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;team-alessandro-masserdotti-vittorio-cuculo-michele-ferretti-maurizio-napolitano&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Team&lt;/strong&gt;: Alessandro Masserdotti, Vittorio Cuculo, Michele Ferretti, Maurizio Napolitano&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 02 May 2011 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/3d-map/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/3d-map/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Imaginary Cities</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In the cartographic tradition the ultimate end is to produce the most accurate-as-possible representation of the physical world. Calvino works as an important evocative reference, but in this field the famous go-to literary reference is Luis Borges’ &lt;em&gt;“Del rigor en la ciencia”&lt;/em&gt;, a short story in which Cartography becomes such a pervasive science that  &lt;em&gt;”..the map of a single Province occupied the entirety of a City, and the map of the Empire, the entirety of a Province.”&lt;/em&gt; almost reaching the impossible dream of a 1:1 representation of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the West, Cartography comes in fact from a scientific and engineering tradition. It served the purpose of land control and regulation, and has very rigorous standards. I quite like that in this project we started from an opposite vision: drawing by hand something completely arbitrary. Something you dream of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is even more interesting if you take into account that, as a mean to the end of of producing our imaginary dream-like cities, we used cutting-edge technology released less than a week ago. In Invisible Cities you can detect a subversion of technology: in this digital age maps are a product of code, something which is often perceived as dry and technical. But by creatively using code you might end up with completely unexpected outcomes. We had drawn the cities, but these are the networks that ultimately “imagined” them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We explored also the opportunity to shed light on social issues by comparing and contrasting extremely diverse cities. Even though there are initiatives supported by humanitarian agencies like The Red Cross and Doctors Without Borders to map “unmapped” places, the stark difference in availability of geographic (open)data in cities from the so-called “developed” and “developing” countries is truly struck. Thus, a natural extension of this project might precisely be to employ this technology to show the incredible, often unfortunate, disparity in our world. And encourage people to think and act upon it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;year-2016&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Year&lt;/strong&gt;: 2016&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;team-gene-kogan-gabriele-gambotto-ambhika-samsen-andrej-boleslavský-michele-ferretti-damiano-gui-fabian-frei&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Team&lt;/strong&gt;: Gene Kogan, Gabriele Gambotto, Ambhika Samsen, Andrej Boleslavský, Michele Ferretti, Damiano Gui, Fabian Frei&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 29 Nov 2010 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/imaginary-cities/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/imaginary-cities/</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>